William (Jingquan), YU

Professional Profile

"An exceptionally professional and outperformed Technical Staff and previous lead consulting expert with Chem. Eng. qualifications, over 7 years of traceable commercial experience and over 1 year experience in academia"

With excellency in technical consulting, worked as previous lead consultant focusing non-metallic materials. Strong project management and the coordination of assets and resources to ensure the smooth progression towards the optimal outcome with highest satisfaction. The combination of concise and effective communication skills, top-tier troubleshooting and abundant practical experience are the key to my well-established reputation and rapports in this field. Stakeholders who benefited from my knowledge and experience are at all levels across bespoke and interdisciplinary regions.

Core Strengths

- Mechanical and Thermal Analysis
- Instron, Shimadzu UTM and auxiliaries
- Rheological analysis
- DSC, MDSC, TGA, TMA, DMA
- Surface Analysis and Fractography
- Material Characterisations with ATR-FTIR, XRD, MFR
- Chemical Compounds and Elemental Analysis HPLC, GC, MS
- Data Analysis & Interpretation
- Analytical Instrument Management, Calibrations
- Project Management
- Team Leader and Lead Technical Consultant
- Great Interpersonal skills
- NATA Report Reviewing & Issuing
- Effective Communications
- Natural Troubleshooting
- Logical & Analytical Thinking
- Agile adoption and application of new concepts and Faster learner
- Teamwork Due Diligence

Career Summary

Apr 2021 – Current

RMIT University, Melbourne, VIC, Australia
Technical Officer (Chemical Process and Environmental Team)

Outline

As a technical officer under the management of senior coordinator, my responsibilities cover the procurement of consumables, undertake machine repair, maintenance and calibration for daily operation and usage. I also play crucial role in supporting learning & teaching as well as research activities with empirical insights, industrial experience and advice on chemical procurement.

Key Responsibilities

- Managing six separate and fully equipped laboratories in rheology, material characterisation and polymer processing.
- Providing technical supports (both instrumental or experimental) to all stakeholder at various levels (from HDR students and researchers to academic staff and industrial partners).
- Undertaking professional management of wide range of analytical instrumentations (from user roster making, training to maintenance and troubleshooting) to accommodate all users' needs as possible.
- Liaising with external supplier for the repair and troubleshooting of instrumentations or the procurement of testing consumables or kits as requested in educational or research activities.

Jan 2021 - Apr 2021

ALS Industrial, Melbourne, VIC, Australia Product Testing Engineer

Outline

As a critical member in product testing team, I directly dealt with internal and external customers to come up with feasible and economical mechanical testing schemes addressing their most urgent concerns. By adhering to industrial or sector standards, the implementation of critical routine tests or checks guarantee the daily operation of production line. Prepared and compiled technical reports in compliance with NATA requirements.

Apr 2015 - Apr 2020

ExcelPlas Pty Ltd, Melbourne, VIC, Australia
Laboratory Technical Supervisor/NATA Signatory/Consulting Expert

Outline

Reported directly to Technical Manager, conducted instrument management (from operation, calibration to maintenance and repair) and delivered quality instrument seminars/workshops to internal and external stakeholders. I confronted with a range of clients on daily test enquiries, delivered quality technical consultancies, managed client relationships, and oversaw the entire laboratory daily operation as well as quality management on project deliverables.

Key Responsibilities

- Undertook technical consultations through the whole project lifecycle and guaranteed quality project deliverables.
- Oversaw daily performance of technicians and provided technical assistance and guidance as request.
- Organised and liaised with external certified stakeholders for scheduled calibration or verification on equipment.
- Performed internal quality auditing, issued, or rejected NATA reports as signatory and compiled quasi-legal reports for failure analysis and litigation disputes.
- Managed client relations, monitored clients' feedback, responded, and acted to disputes and conflicts.
- Liaised with local and overseas scientific entities (universities, government agencies, laboratories, and regulators) for project collaboration.

Key Achievements

- Successfully delivered several failure analysis and litigation dispute projects with well-known firms in last year.
- Maintained and repaired several critical instrumentations which reduced a significant amount of unnecessary cost.
- Novel analysis and solutions were innovated and considered as efficient in-house methods which was widely recognised by peers and organisations.

Apr 2014 - Apr 2015

ExcelPlas Pty Ltd, Melbourne, VIC, Australia **Senior Laboratory Technician**

Outline

Undertook routine, standard, non-standard experiments on polymer products (eg. Geomembranes, geosynthetics, raw resin pellets, injection moulded or compression moulded parts etc.). Highly specialised in mechanical equipment (UTM with extensometers/static thermal chambers, impact tester), thermal and rheological analyzers (DSC, MDSC, TGA, TMA, DMA and rheometers from TA instrument), durability testing (QUV tester, fatigue tester etc.).

Apr 2012 - May 2013 Symbio Alliance, Brisbane, QLD, Australia

Senior Laboratory Technician

Education

M.Eng.	Masters in Chemical Engineering (Distinctive)	Dec 2011
	The University of Adelaide (UoA), Australia	
B.Eng.	Bachelor in Chemical Engineering (Hons, High Distinctive, 1st in class)	Jun 2009
	Weifang University, China	

Computer Skills & Languages

MS Excel, Word and PowerPoint (Engineering use)

English (Fluent)

Python (Numpy, Pandas, Tensorflow, Keras, Qiskit Modules)

Mandarin (Native Speaker)

References

Tzu-ying Kuo Senior Technical Officer Swinburne University of Technology Tel: 0491 156 052

Email: tkuo@swin.edu.au Relationship: Previous colleague/team member

Steve Shamis Australian Sales and Service Manager **TA Instruments** Tel: 0413 749 030

Email: sshamis@tainstruments.com Relationship: Current external

stakeholder

Xiaobo Chen Senior Lecturer **RMIT University** Tel: 03 9925 6038

Email: Xiaobo.chen@rmit.edu.au Relationship: Stakeholder (academic)